A Guide to the Eugene Scheel Research Collection, ca. 1900-1999
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Eugene Scheel Research Collection ca. 1900-1999
Thomas Balch Library
VC 0031
The Eugene Scheel Research Collection is a mixed-media collection of articles by Scheel, publications used by him in his research and classes, reproduction photographs, and digital surrogates of photographs retained by their owners. Many images in the collection appeared in various of Scheel's publications. It is an open collection.
Eugene Scheel
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Eugene Scheel, Waterford, VA
Alternative Form Available
Electronic media
Accruals
2005.0192, 2007.0161, 2007.0199, 2009.0159, 2011.0272, 2012.0090
Biographical Information
Originally from the Bronx, New York, longtime Virginia resident Eugene Scheel is the creator of dozens of hand-drawn maps covering Virginia, other states and foreign nations, as well as the author of numerous books and articles on Virginia history. He writes a history column for The Washington Post, is a frequent contributor to The Portolan, a publication of the Washington Map Society, and has taught Loudoun school teachers "history-in-the-field" courses relating the local scene to its broader context for thirty-five years.
Scheel earned a Bachelor of Arts from Clark University, Worcester, Massachusetts in Geography, a Master of Urban and Environmental Planning from the University of Virginia, and a Master of Arts from Georgetown University in American Literature. After spending eight years in the Marine Reserves, Scheel worked for Rand McNally and Company in Chicago and with the National Geographic Society before entering into private practice.
Scope and Content
The Eugene Scheel Research Collection is a mixed-media collection of articles by Scheel, publications used by him in his research and classes, reproduction photographs, and digital surrogates of photographs retained by their owners. Many images in the collection appeared in various of Scheel's publications. It is an open collection.
The Roger Powell, Ezekial Mount house, Mountville Store, Crossroads School, and Middleburg School photographs are reproduction photographs; some have digital surrogates as well. The remaining images are digital surrogates only. See PastPerfect catalogue, vc_0031_0001-vc_0031_0014 for digital surrogates.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Eugene Scheel Research Collection, ca. 1900-(M 074), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA
Lewis-Edwards Architectural Surveys of Loudoun County 1972-2007 (M 022), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA
Scheel, Eugene M. Loudoun Discovered: Communities, Corners & Crossroads. Vol. 5, Waterford, the German Settlement and Between the Hills and Vol. 3, The Hunt Country and Middleburg. Leesburg, VA: Friends of the Thomas Balch Library, 2002
Scheel, Eugene M. Telephone interview by Beth Schuster, 29 August 2009.
Location of Originals
Retained by owners. See individual accession records.
Other Finding Aid
PastPerfect catalogue records
Technical Requirements
Electronic media
Related Material
Roger Powell Collection, 1790-1996 (M 037); Roger F. Powell Letter (SC 0047); Eugene Scheel, Loudoun Discovered: Communities, Corners & Crossroads, V REF 975.528 SCH
Contents List
- (M 074)
  - Articles: "British Planning: Approaches of two nations are compared." 1973
  - Articles: [Architectural Styles of Northern Piedmont of Virginia], ca. 1985
  - Articles: "A Chronology of Events Important to the African Americans of Loudon County, Virginia," February, 1999
  - Articles: "Evolution of Style: A History of Building," draft and photocopy of published version, 1981
  - Certificate parodies created by Eugene Scheel, 1999 and n.d.
  - Publications: "Amateur's Guide to Terms Commonly Used in Describing Historic Buildings," by Harley J. McKee for The Landmark Society, 1970
  - Publications: Loudoun Almanac: News and Information from Loudoun Healthcare, Spring 1997 and July 1997.
  - Publications: Loudoun Broadside: Loudoun County Independent Bicentennial Committee, (1 issue) 1975-1976
  - Publications: "Phase I Survey of the Proposed Park Development in the Signal Hill and Union Mill Tracts, City of Manassas Park, Pince William County, Virginia," by Thomas E. McGarry and Associates, May 1983.
- (VC 0031)
  - Roger Powell photographs (3 photographs)
    Used in "Sheriff and Storyteller, Roger Powell Kept Little-Known Pieces of the Past Alive," The Washington Post, 2 Sep 2001, p. T-03.
  - Ezekiel Mount House, Mountville Store, Crossroads School (5 photographs)
    Ezekiel Mount House & Crossroads School used in Loudoun Discovered, volumes 3 and 5, respectively.
  - Middleburg School, 1911 (Copy; original belongs to Loudoun County Public Schools)
  - (Digital Photographs)
    - [African-American school children], ca. 1935
    - [Margaret Tavenner on horseback], ca. 1925
    - [Singhas & Michael Corp drilling on-site], n.d.
      Used in "Well Driller Has Made His Mark All Over Loudoun," The Washington Post, 18 Apr 2009, p. T-8.
    - [Snapshot of Robert E. Butt], ca. 1970
    - [Snapshot of Robert E. Butt], ca. 1985
      Used in "When Loudoun Schools Closed the Book on the Past," The Washington Post, 30 August 2009, p. T-7.
    - Workshop [teachers' workshop at Douglass High School] 1948